<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yehya-farhat.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://yehya-farhat.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-09-18T06:28:47+00:00</updated><id>https://yehya-farhat.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal Website; Machine Learning, Combinatorial Optimization, Yehya Farhat. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">What are the machines learning?</title><link href="https://yehya-farhat.github.io/blog/2023/MLmodels/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What are the machines learning?"/><published>2023-09-17T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-17T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yehya-farhat.github.io/blog/2023/MLmodels</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yehya-farhat.github.io/blog/2023/MLmodels/"><![CDATA[<style>.image-container{height:200px;overflow:hidden}.image-container img{width:100%;height:100%;object-fit:cover}</style> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <div class="image-container"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/robotimghands-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/robotimghands-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/robotimghands-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/robotimghands.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <div class="image-container"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/mathfuncs-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/mathfuncs-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/mathfuncs-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/mathfuncs.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <p><br/></p> <p> With the recent surge of AI models, from Chatgpt to Googles latest search embedded generative AI, This technology is here stay. Looking ahead, AI systems will be industry staples. A standard tool used by every company, home, and individual. Akin to the ubiquity of computers today. AI prompting skills will probably be the next Microsoft office skills you see required in every day job postings. With the speed this technology is moving its essential to take a step back and look at what these models actually are and why they're so useful ! </p> <h2 id="the-domain-of-ai">The domain of AI</h2> <p> Before delving into the world of AI, it's crucial to establish clarity in our terminology. The terms Machine Learning (ML), Artificial Intelligence (AI), and Deep Learning are often used interchangeably, leading to confusion. In essence, AI serves as an umbrella term, akin to "Biology," which encompasses a wide range of subdomains and techniques. AI is often employed as a buzzword for securing funding, but it signifies a broad and multifaceted field. Within the realm of AI, Machine Learning stands out as its crown jewel. Machine Learning itself comprises a diverse array of techniques, each with its own unique characteristics and applications. One of the most renowned and potent branches of Machine Learning is Deep Learning, also known as neural networks. Deep Learning techniques have gained widespread recognition for their ability to handle complex tasks and are at the forefront of many AI breakthroughs. <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/AIdomain-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/AIdomain-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/AIdomain-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/AIdomain.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Here's a nice image to visualize this hierarchy, machine learning encompasses a multitude of techniques: Decision Trees, Linear regression, Support Vector Machine (SVM), and deep learning (just to name a few). deep learning is a field of its own as its one of the most successful ML algorithms. You will find a lot of variation there, from convolutional neural networks (Imaging) to Transformers (Language). But essentially everything i just named falls under the same umbrella term; ML. But how do ML models work and what are these algorithms doing? </p> <p><br/></p> <h2 id="what-does-linear-regression-and-deep-neural-networks-have-in-common">What does Linear regression and Deep Neural Networks have in common?</h2> <p>Spoiler, Linear Regression and Deep Neural Networks are both Machine learning algorithms.<br/> But what does something you might have studied in high school have to do with the architecture behind Chatgpt? Essentially these two algorithms are trying to do exactly the same thing, just in very different ways.</p> <p>The goal behind both these techniques, and every other ML technique you will come across is that they’re all trying to estimate (“Learn”) a mapping of the given dataset, or in other words they’re trying to find the function \(f(x)\) that describes your data. More formally, given the input data \(X\) and the output data \(Y\) find me an \(f(X)\) that best describes that mapping. The more data points you provide, the better your estimate.</p> <p>Thats it! that is literally all these models are doing. Well okay, theres a lot more that goes into it, but on a high level that is all you need to know. Its essence is a statistical technique, give me a bunch of points and ill try and find you the best function that describes/maps the data points.</p> <p>I will not be diving into how linear regression or neural networks work. those are very long topics that deserve their own posts, and frankly you will find endless resources about them online. We will simply look into what they do without diving into all the technical details of “how” they do it. Hopefully by the end of this post i hope to demonstrate why these techniques are very useful and why they’re being used in every domain right now.</p> <p>Lets have a quick refresher of what mathematical functions are.</p> <h4>Functions</h4> <p>Here’s the definition of a function i shamelessly stole from wikipedia. <br/> In mathematics, a function from a set \(X\) to a set \(Y\) assigns to each element of \(X\) one element of \(Y\). The set of \(X\) is called the domain of the function and the set \(Y\) is called the codomain or range of the function.</p> <p>So in layman terms, you can think of a function as a sort of machine. You give it a certain input, \(x\) it does some manipulation to the given input and spits out an output \(y\). Its also good to note that almost all of scientific theories are built upon functions. From quantum mechanical descriptions to tumor growth rates.</p> <p>Heres an example of a simple function: \(f(x) = x^2\) <br/> Whatever number you give this function it will multiply it by itself and give you the corresponding answer \(2 \rightarrow f(2) \rightarrow 4\) <br/></p> <p>Functions are usually derived via empirical observations or mathematically from some set of rules. Einstein for example, derived his famous \(E=mc^2\) equation by stabilizing the speed of light and voilà! You now have a function to describe the relation between mass and energy. You plug in a value for the mass and you will in turn get a value of the energy or if you want to go the opposite way, you plug in energy and you will get the mass.</p> <p>But as we said you can also derive equations purely based on empirical observation (and some intuition of course). If you want to Model population growth, you look at your data and come up with an equation that best describes the population data you have at hand. This technique is usually a bit harder, because it involves a lot more of trial and error and is prone to biased estimation of the sample data you have at hand (foreshadowing much?) That is not to say that deriving equations is easier, theres a lot of trial and error there too and those theories are also biased is their own way. We don’t need to look too far, take Newtons work on gravity. His equations could not describe pluto’s orbit or the bending of light due to gravitational affect, Newton simply did not have that data available to test his theory and had to make due with an apple and a moon.</p> <h4>Find me the functions</h4> <p>Here, lets try to derive an equations from empirical observation . I will give you a bunch if points, find the Function (Pattern)!</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>\(X\)</th> <th style="text-align: center">\(Y\)</th> <th> </th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>1</td> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>2</td> <td style="text-align: center">8</td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>3</td> <td style="text-align: center">27</td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>4</td> <td style="text-align: center">64</td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>\(\vdots\)</td> <td style="text-align: center">\(\vdots\)</td> <td><br/></td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>You probably guessed it, the function is \(f(x) = x^3\), you simply multiply the number by itself three times.</p> <p>Good, let’s complicate our example. This time, our function takes two positive inputs. To simplify matters, we’ll set the second input (\(Z\)) as a constant value. This function may remind you of something you encountered in high school physics. Your task is to work with this function with the constant Z and determine the relationship between the two variables that best describes it.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>\(X;Z\)</th> <th style="text-align: center">\(Y\)</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>1 ; 9.8</td> <td style="text-align: center">9.8</td> </tr> <tr> <td>10 ; 9.8</td> <td style="text-align: center">98</td> </tr> <tr> <td>4 ; 9.8</td> <td style="text-align: center">39.2</td> </tr> <tr> <td>7 ; 9.8</td> <td style="text-align: center">68.6</td> </tr> <tr> <td>\(\vdots\)</td> <td style="text-align: center">\(\vdots\)</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>This was also a straight giveaway from the first input. You multiply the two numbers together. looks a bit like Newtons second law, no? \(F=ma\). Just set “a” to 9.8 (acceleration of Earth’s gravity).</p> <p>I’ve been providing relatively straightforward examples so far, with inputs given in a specific order and corner cases to aid in deduction. Now, let’s consider a different scenario. I’ll present a function that takes positive inputs, but this time, the data isn’t sorted, and I won’t offer any obvious hints. Your challenge is to determine the function that most accurately represents this data.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>\(X;Z\)</th> <th style="text-align: center">\(Y\)</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>7 ; 2</td> <td style="text-align: center">7.82</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3 ; 9</td> <td style="text-align: center">9.42</td> </tr> <tr> <td>5 ; 6</td> <td style="text-align: center">7.81</td> </tr> <tr> <td>4 ; 8</td> <td style="text-align: center">8.94</td> </tr> <tr> <td>2 ; 2</td> <td style="text-align: center">2.83</td> </tr> <tr> <td>10 ; 15</td> <td style="text-align: center">18.03</td> </tr> <tr> <td>8 ; 9</td> <td style="text-align: center">12.04</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3 ; 7</td> <td style="text-align: center">7.62</td> </tr> <tr> <td>\(\vdots\)</td> <td style="text-align: center">\(\vdots\)</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>If you found this then i salute you, If you didn’t i don’t blame you. This function would have taken some time to find. The function in question is the famous pythagorean theorem. \(x^2 + z^2 = y^2\)<br/></p> <p>The exercises I’ve presented so far were merely illustrative examples. None of these functions necessarily had to be derived in this particular manner. However, consider what happens when we encounter a scenario where we genuinely need to do this. What if we possess a dataset of a specific function but lack any insight into the actual function itself? You can appreciate how challenging this can become for us, ordinary humans.<br/></p> <p>Let’s explore a real-life situation where this challenge is indeed applicable: image classification! Here’s the scenario: can you provide me with a function that takes as input an image containing either a cat or a dog and outputs either 0, to signify a cat, or 1, to denote a dog? An image is essentially represented mathematically as an array that encodes pixel values. However, you don’t need to focus on the technical details of this representation. The critical point here is that our function takes an input matrix, denoted as A, which describes the pixel content of the image.</p> <p>For clarity, let’s consider \(A_1\) as the matrix representing a dog image and \(A_0\) as the matrix representing a cat image. Your task is to provide the function that best captures the relationship between these input matrices to distinguish between cat and dog images accurately.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>\(X\)</th> <th style="text-align: center">\(Y\)</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>\(A_0\)</td> <td style="text-align: center">0</td> </tr> <tr> <td>\(A_1\)</td> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>This is already getting into the realm of impossibility and its even more challenging when we consider that we’ve only had to deal with two inputs and two outputs. Now, picture the complexity of classifying ten different animals, each captured from slightly different angles. <br/></p> <p>This is where the value of ML models truly shines. Each ML model offers a unique representation of the underlying function. For example, deep neural networks discover weight matrices, while K-Means Clustering identifies points in a hypergraph. Regardless of the specific technique, these models perform numerous calculations that would likely have taken you years to do yourself to manually derive arbitrary set of representations to effectively describe the data.</p> <p>Where do you see this technology going?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="MachineLearning"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What are machine learning models actually learning, and why are they so useful?]]></summary></entry></feed>